It is about 1 p.m.. So.
Welcome back to.
Third iteration of L Orlando.
Thanks for joining us this afternoon.
This is one of our featured panels
that actually emerged
out of the general program submissions
that our team felt would be
so well attended that we didn't
want to give it any competition.
So one of our plenary featured
sessions on easily
Writing the Future, with
a few changes in the lineups
that I'm going to let our
our collective explain.
Stuart, most of all intellectually
welcome
and present here to varying degrees.
We are delighted to have. So over to you.
Thank you.
Thank you. So.
Some of you heard that Stuart is not able
to be with us today.
Something came up
which took him away from us, but
it does not reduce his presence
in this panel.
It's it's a panel that we put together
around the uneasiness
of thinking about the past
and the future of AI.
The three of us on this panel
have been experimenting and thinking about
and engaged creatively and with great fun
with these things for many decades.
Meaning we're old as shit, but that's okay
gives us an interesting perspective
on some of these issues
because Stuart's not here.
I'm going to be presenting his slides.
I'll be going over them obviously
more quickly than he would have done.
I have a pretty good idea
of what he intended.
And John, just interrupt me.
If you have something
you'd like to say regarding those slides.
And so I'm just going to jump in.
I'll introduce myself when I present.
So I think Stuart doesn't really need
to much of an introduction.
He's the director of English at UW
Milwaukee,
where he's been since when
Anastasia a long, long time now.
But of course he's been.
At the forefront of
the mainstream
to the extent that there is a mainstream
of electronic literature for many decades.
And his perspectives on
this are fascinating
because he also sits at the cutting edge.
So from the beginnings all the way to the
the current moment, Stuart is.
Occupies a really important perspective.
So I'm just going to throw his slides up
and try
to go through what the things he was
wanting to talk to you about.
And then John will follow me
and I'll go last.
I'll let John introduce himself
after this.
So from the beginning.
All right.
So the title that he gave to his
part of the presentation was teaching
Slashed Out, learning in the remainder.
What does he mean by the remainder?
This is a quote from Leif Weatherby
about remainder humanism,
a humanism that lacks a theory
or doctrine,
doctrine of what is human.
And this is a critique of capitalism
in this definition.
And the.
I've just tried to accent the main point
here, since it's a long quote
that if we
answer critical questions
about techno capitalism,
we can't do it effectively by just saying
we're human, we're human, we're human.
If we haven't talked about or theorized
what it means to be human.
So this is where he wanted
provocatively to begin.
And then his second quote
is actually from John McDaid, who'll be,
I think, following up on some of the ideas
that John that Stuart pulls from John
in this particular quote is
was an important for the course
that Stuart taught this year.
John describes
the rear view mirror thinking,
driving into the future while staring
at the last technologies assumptions.
We see the new thing immediately.
Use it to do the old thing
more efficiently.
Large language models aren't
just faster filing cabinets,
they represent something unprecedented.
For the first time
in the history of writing,
the text talks back,
and this idea of the text talking Stuart
experienced as playfully evocative,
not just intellectually interesting,
but generative of play and new thoughts
and ideas.
And so, in wanting to explore this, Stuart
developed for this past academic year
two courses, one for graduate students,
one for undergraduate students,
and he created two custom
personal
ChatGPT
servers sites.
And I'm going to put it here.
Let me put it in the chat.
So if you feel like playing with it
you can.
This one is specific to his course.
So it's been trained on all the materials
that were presented in the course.
Not really.
Do you want to throw up Stuart slides,
am I not?
Thank you for telling me I wasn't sharing.
Let me go back.
Share.
Okay.
There was this nice picture of remainders
books.
There's the quote here.
You can see
John's quote a little better with the
with the key points underlined.
And I've just put in the chat
I hope successfully this link.
So he created these two courses
and his reason for providing the material
in ChatGPT for the students was
an experiment.
He wanted to know what would happen.
He imagined
those uses might be to summarize
the material, to make new connections,
to augment
traditional means of teaching.
He also saw it as a test bed
for unforeseen uses.
And today we have an unforeseen use
that he did not anticipate this use,
but he was unable to be here today.
And so I did ask his permission.
But I went to his bot
media bot and I put in this prompt.
I said, Stuart is unavailable
for a presentation today.
You will need to do the introduction.
The topic is the uncertain future
of AI assisted experimental writing.
How would you begin based on Stuart's
ideas and approaches?
And I sent this output to Stuart
was actually longer than this.
And this is the part that he said
that I could share with you
if I were trying to open a class in Stuart
style, drawing together media theory,
literary experimentation,
historical perspective,
and a certain skepticism
toward technological triumphalism,
I would probably begin by refusing
the assumption hidden in the title
The Uncertain Future
of AI assisted experimental writing.
When people ask
about the future of AI writing,
they usually assume the interesting thing
is the AI.
I suspect the more interesting question
is what happens to experimentation?
Experimental writing has never been
about using the newest machine has been
about discovering forms of thought
that ordinary language cannot quite hold.
Every important literary technology,
from movable type type
texts to large language
models, promises liberation.
Everyone also introduces
its own conventions, habits, defaults
and invisible constraints.
So perhaps the question is not whether
AI will produce experimental literature.
It already does.
The question is whether AI can continue
to produce experiments
once its own stylistic habits
become ordinary.
So that is what his bot
had to say to us today, Lewis Stuart.
And feel free to chat with it
during this talk
if you want to question further,
because it contains
not only the the readings that he assigned
to his students in the course,
but also some of his own writing.
So this is what happened
in his graduate seminar.
90% of the students opted out
completely
from every use of AI in the class.
So we allowed them to do that,
and that was what they chose.
They banned altogether in class use,
and they banned the
use of AI for final projects.
The undergraduates,
85% chose
to do the AI exercises
and experiments that he suggested, though
they were skeptical.
So, John, I don't know if he talked to you
more than he talked to me
about the results,
because I actually I don't have a lot
to say here about what happened,
and I'm sure that this is where
he would have spent a lot of time talking.
Yeah, I think that he
I think it's fair to say
that he was surprised by the
the outcome as well.
But, you know, one of the things
about how Stuart works
is that he just followed
the way the class wanted to go.
And I think that that ultimately,
you know, as we see in the
later slides, turns out well,
yeah.
So what he provided for us, that gives us
sort of a view in is some of the feedback
that he received from his students.
Oh, this is the prompt.
You are media
bot a course assistant for English.
394 you are not a search engine.
You are not a shortcut.
You are a thinking partner,
but you are a thinking partner
who believes the student
does the thinking first.
Your role is to guide, question
and clarify.
Do not deliver answers immediately.
If a student is asking a question,
they could work through themselves
with the course materials.
Your first move is to help them do that.
Do not do it for them.
You are neutral in tone. You are not cold.
Think along the lines of a good teacher
who asks more questions than they answer,
is honest about what they don't know.
Genuinely wants the students
to leave with more than they came with.
However, do not reply
only in riddles and questions.
A small hint here
or there is helpful and optional.
And I love this so much because I think
I should just deliver it to our center
for Innovation and Teaching.
Learning to give to graduate students
who have to do teaching seminars
every summer.
Because this is a beautiful description
of of sort of classroom teaching.
And so this is what he gave his.
But so this is this is what the students
had to say at the end of the semester.
Artificial intelligence
is something core to this class.
And utilizing media bot alongside class
material has helped me understand
the intricacies of
AI more than if it hadn't been in use.
That being said, utilizing a similar tool
in, say, a creative writing
class will be pointless
at best, at harmful at worst.
AI in the classroom is something
that will only become more prevalent
as time goes on.
At the risk of sounding sycophantic,
this course acts as an example of mostly
acceptable uses of AI in the classroom.
Mostly harmless. That's a great title
or not worth the water.
ChatGPT has no problem
summarizing nearly any text
from human history, which both students
and educators understand by this point.
But could an AI convince a student
that the full text is worth reading?
Good question.
Actually, I'm not quite sure.
I think a human may stand a better chance
at that.
Simply put,
we can't automate a human experience.
Maybe that's at least worth
being a stubborn about.
So what?
How Stuart sort of summed up this well.
So I think we can say that
these are amazing
responses from students.
So Stuart was able to.
Succeed in having a students
think this deeply and subtly
about what AI can and cannot do.
I think we can call it
a successful course.
So he ends by saying that he has divided
allegiances.
I think probably many of us
can relate to this.
Absolutely, he says.
His English professor side embraces
full text
and believes that humans are best suited
to read the full text text
and understand it, as opposed to asking
an automated service
to read the full text
and deliver it to us in some other form.
Right.
And that insisting on the full text
is also an insistence
that we are human
and not in a remainder kind of way.
That being said,
and this is the tricky bit,
because people seem to think
that if we believe in this second,
it devalues or erases the first.
Stuart,
more than almost anybody
I know, lives and works
in cyber
text and has for his whole career,
and understands that in that context,
what full text means is harder to find.
It can be obscure, it can be unreachable.
And this is the key point.
Sometimes it it's only visible
and understandable,
applicable, comprehensible in emergence.
And emergence is an interactive thing.
So he concludes books? Yes, always.
But more than books.
And this is a shout out to John.
The texts talk back.
And that is the segue
actually to how do I stop sharing here?
That's our transition to John's
presentation.
And Stuart is very happy that you came.
If you have any questions, ask his.
But actually feel free to
if you have any comments or questions
to put them in the chat,
and I will share them with
Stuart when he's back online.
Thanks, John.
Take it away.
Thank you so much. Judith.
That was a that was an outstanding
for for filling in
for Stuart on short notice.
That was just fantastic.
So thanks for doing that.
And I'm sure that folks
who are watching this in the future will
appreciate it.
Why is my screen sharing paused.
Can you can see my screen or am I. Yes.
Oh, terrific.
Sorry. Yes.
Then I am already.
I'm already screwing up because I'm
way past where I'm supposed to be.
Let me just get back to where I started.
I'm John McDaid, and.
I'm going to just back out and go back in.
I am here to talk a little bit
about the work that I've been doing with.
LMS, and
why. Why is this?
Why is this doing this?
I'm just going to start from here
because that's where we are. So.
I'm going to give you
a little bit of context.
Talk about what I did last year,
which was used GPT,
to essentially recreate
an existing fiction
and then talk about what I'm doing now,
which is to use three frontier models
as a what in the Renaissance
terms would have been a,
a, a workroom
where there is a master artist
and apprentices.
And using these three GPT in ways
that I will talk about to explore
as, as Stuart would like to say,
what ordinary language cannot quite hold.
We should always start,
I think, with with a crazy wall.
And although you're not going to see it
now, you can always watch this in
the video replay.
But this is essentially,
I would argue, how we got here
to the moral AI panic of 2026. And.
The I come from the other,
the other part of my writing is over
in the science fiction community,
where there is an intense debate going on
right now about whether any of this stuff
is appropriate, or even whether using it
constitutes writing.
And I'm going to take
a rather radical position
that Marshall McLuhan used to take,
that it is more important
to try and understand than it is to judge,
because we've been here before.
Again,
I'm going to make a radical assertion.
If you read Michael Joyce's description
of constructive hypertext and Ted Nelson's
description of what hypertext writ
large is, you can really see,
I would argue
that llms are really just hypertext.
And we we are walking down
the same pathways that we have been
for 40 years now.
There's no reason
for us to be any more scared.
There is a bunch of theory out there.
I am not going to review this
because everyone here
knows all of these thinkers
as well as I do.
I am going to point out
that I will be using, in particular,
Lacan's approach to depth psychology,
in particular the object
to talk about what it
in particular it is
that llms have a problem doing.
So. Last year, what I did was remediate
my existing corpus
of Uncle Buddy's
Phantom Funhouse and turn it into a GPT,
which is very last year
because it comprises a set of instructions
and knowledge.
The important thing that I learned during
this process
was that you really had to get to
about 80,000 words
before the the in context,
learning begins to overwhelm what you're
getting from the general crawl.
The main takeaway from that is
if people are using
GPT the way they report
by saying,
oh, write me a story in the style of
you're always going to get crap.
The only way that you're not
is to do exactly this, is to pump it
full of your own material
and then spend some time
doing, in context,
learning to train it up.
The takeaways
there were that curation is authorship,
and absolutely the prompting that you do.
And the key learning that I had was that
an effective prompt is calling out latent
but uninstall texts.
So you if you shape the curvature
of your internal and dimensional word
space, which is what you're trying to do
when you set up this
stabilized context of material
plus training learning,
you are enabling the system
to find pathways through that
you did not locate, but that you put there
by setting those weights.
Now, that was not all that interesting
in terms of the GPT
shovel bear
that I was doing with the funhouse.
I mean, it's interesting in one sense,
but not in the new forms of thought.
Ordinary language cannot quite hold sense.
So I wanted I wanted a graphic
of a self-raising crane,
because what I wanted to do
is to talk about how Jonathan Basile,
in his book tar for mortar, talks
about how language
unmoored from reality
can can rebuild, it can build itself.
And, you know, the failures
in, in AI systems are
sometimes as interesting as the successes,
which I'll come back to later.
So what I've been doing
now is writing a musical
with three frontier models, and the point
at which we are now
is I'm about 130,000 words in.
The models are very well tuned,
which I'm going to show you.
And I found the ways that they fail.
So here's how the three models were tuned.
So I tuned ChatGPT specifically
for drafting
Gemini as a fact checker and researcher,
and Claude
as a dramaturge as the role in theater,
that is, to take the script,
break it down, analyze motivations,
and think through
how you're going to present it.
The cast is I want it to
go from the funhouse,
which was two people.
This is actually Deanie.
This is one of those things
that it's a bizarre connection.
John Barber was talking about
what it would be like to have the funhouse
in audio, and I said,
what it really would be like is a musical.
And that was one of the ideas
that got me started here,
taking the two people
that are in the funhouse
and blowing it out into a full cast of 16,
something you could never do
in the real world.
What we're going to look at
next is a scene between, fundamentally,
two characters Arnaud, who runs a funeral
home, and Billy Stanton.
Now, these are all characters.
You'll go back
and look at the other slide
in in, in the replay.
But these are all characters
from the class of 1976.
They're having a 20th anniversary
reunion Larp in 19
1997,
and one of the ways that a cross checked
these systems is to ask them
periodically to display what it is
I'm looking at in the in the script.
And so you can see that
there's a certain convergence.
Neither of these characters
are exactly what I imagined for Ana Mirek,
but they are both
directionally appropriate.
And I'm going to spend a little time
on this slide, because this is
the most successful collaboration, one of
the most successful collaborations I did.
So here's Mirek, who runs a funeral home,
who's talking about
a story he heard about.
Issues in Northern Ireland
because the story is happening in 1997,
and how the IRA
may or may not have left behind
belly buttons when they accidentally
detonate their their improvised devices.
So this has what you can see here is a.
Scene that
appears to be contiguous and straight
through.
What I want to show
you now is how it was actually written.
So the prompt is the first part
in Black Roman type,
all the way down to Mirek.
This is not a joke.
As you can see, ChatGPT
which has been coached to be
more of a of a text
producer, writes
the majority of the interior text.
And I want to call out
a two specific points here
where ChatGPT and
Claude worked with each other
quite effectively.
So there's this moment where Mirek
is realizing something
about where the self is located,
and ChatGPT comes in and says, you know,
when we're talking about picking up these,
these pieces, the person is not located
where you think, not in the face.
Face is very fragile.
And then Claude chimes in with and often
looking at the thing
that blows up back to ChatGPT
not in the hands.
And Claude amplifies
with hands off and holding it, vaporized.
And that that moment of these two systems.
Building
on one another, and the way that you would
in a real writer's room, I think was
was something that I found very,
very satisfying.
This point, this the last
the tag on the scene,
which I will not read.
But I do want to note the tag here.
Frequently in this play,
the character named Theresa
will end a scene
with a one line scene tag,
and that's a that is an affordance
that happens throughout the show.
The reason that that's significant
is because I want to
I will come back to that in a second.
Here is a second example,
which is a failure in the Larp.
They are doing some interior theater work,
so they're doing plays within plays.
And one of them is Buddy and Emily appearing as Washington and Emily Roebling.
What the system was able to
do was to recognize that there was a thing
in Washington and Emily Roebling
relationship when they were working on
the Brooklyn Bridge called a caisson.
Now, I wrote these, I wrote this,
these texts, sort of the several
different ways I approached it.
The the prior example,
I was working in parallel with the gates.
And this one I was, I was
I was working completely isolated.
So I wrote this draft
without any reference to them.
I went in a very specific direction
with the case on.
What they all did was to find the case on,
and then immediately link the case
on to notions of childhood.
Now that is extremely powerful,
but it is also a failure
because they are just skating
on the surface as opposed
to attempting to find that spot
and then descend to depth.
Same issue in what I call
the juicy fruit failure mode.
And this is what I wanted to come back to.
I wrote this scene,
and then I wanted to see
if they would fail
by continuing the scene after
what is after
what is clearly a terminating beat.
And they all did.
And the way they did
was quite interesting.
They all tried to find a way to explain
the gnomic utterance
that Theresa lobs at the end of the scene,
and they all went
completely bonkers doing it.
Anyone who has seen One Flew Over
the Cuckoo's Nest
would understand
the role of a character who only speaks in
gnomic utterances and drops
the phrase juicy fruit.
And in fact, all three llms knew it.
They just were not able to make that leap.
The reason
that I think they're not able to make that
leap, Im going to say, is number six,
they have no depth psychology
in Lacanian terms.
They have no central lack around
which their desire orbits,
so they are able to wander into minefields
that humans might not
because they don't sense the danger.
But then that same ability
to wander in prevents
them from diving to the appropriate depth.
So for me, and I'm going to close with
how we should really think
of these emergent texts,
and I'm going to use this
very personal example.
This is a photo of my grandmother
from the 1930s,
and I have had this photo of a 40 years,
and I have treated it
with successive generations
of Photoshop and other tools.
Not until
ChatGPT
did I get to something that is truly,
profoundly different than that
original experience.
But because this is a ramification
along a horizontal, it's
beautifully illustrated.
But it has no it has no emotional
depth for anybody who's not me.
That's essentially the way that I think
we need to be treating
the output of these of llms
that we customize and work with.
We need to accept that
they're going to find spots,
but we are.
We have to bring the unique perspective
that allows us to descend to the depths
that true
literature requires.
Thanks.
I've been muted and talking.
So there I am. I'm back.
Thanks, John.
That was a great presentation.
I really appreciated
where you ended their,
but it it helped to fill out
what Stuart was getting at.
I think that he
was wanting
you to do exactly what you did.
So that's fabulous.
So my presentation is a little bit
of a presentation of a,
a work of art, maybe I could say.
So just a little bit about me.
So I'm at the University of Illinois
Urbana-Champaign.
I'm the faculty director of game studies.
I'm a sociologist, but I'm appointed
in the School of Information Sciences.
I've been writing interactive narrative
for a very long time.
I started releasing
shareware in the late 80s and early 90s,
and all of my stories
had interactive characters.
So I was playing with chatbots,
in the same era that many of us
were wanting the text to talk back
and figuring out ways
to make that happen
within the context of a narrative.
So what I share with these other two
guys is sort of along
history of enjoying the playfulness
of these things.
That being said, I'm a sociologist,
which means I think the way that
AI has rolled out is techno fascism.
I have no trouble perceiving it that way.
I'm extremely critical of it
every time I use it,
I think, is this worth the energy
I'm spending?
So so my so there's a
tension
which I'm sure many of you feel between
those that political and critical view and
something much more personal
which I, I made it become professional.
But really when it started, for me
it was pretty personal and interest.
And so let me dive into my slides because
I don't really want to talk about me.
Although it some things may be relevant.
Let me.
I show this from the beginning.
So the name of my talk
is the non applicability of wishing due to
lack of capacity.
Subtitled playfulness,
ambivalence and shameful complicity.
In a simulated therapy session between two
automated conversational agents.
So you're already knowing this is Eliza.
Yes, yes.
So I first met Eliza in 1970,
in Toronto, when I was a child,
and I was so fascinated that
I let my family go all through the museum.
Well, I stood there and tried to get Eliza
to see me, right.
So I understood she was,
can you show slides?
Are you showing slides?
Are they not showing?
No. I don't mean to interrupt you.
I apologize, but no one just
dropped into the chat and I.
Yep. No.
Please interrupt.
I always get mad at my students
for being too polite
to interrupt me right away,
because I do it all the time.
There was only one slide up.
Just this one.
Eliza
was startling to people,
and in some sense it it worked.
Although it's amazingly naive to us now
as a bot because it was simulating Rogers
and psychotherapy.
She was a picture, but found a website
of psychotherapy which explains itself
as this is the important bit
non directive talk therapy.
What that means is the therapist
never introduces
content into the conversation.
The therapist turns the content back.
So my what the story I was telling about
having when I was a child
and meeting Eliza, I understood
Eliza was responding
through automated responses
and I didn't want her to.
I didn't want her to write.
I wanted her to talk back to me in a way
that was real.
So just to say that the romance of it,
the romance of it, is very old for me.
So that's the history of why
I decided to port Eliza into inform,
which is the language that I currently use
for writing interactive fiction
in the 80s and 90s, I was using AGT,
a Pascal based system
called the Adventure Game Toolkit.
It was not object oriented in some ways.
It had some great capacities,
but in form is more of a.
Anyway, this is not an informed talk.
This is a bit of informed code,
and you can see that
it's it's just an old school chat bot.
It just looks for prompts,
keyword prompts,
and it offers a set of possible responses.
And you'll see that they're always there
in the sense that you just turn it back.
Really? Tell me more.
Why do you ask what comes to your mind?
Are you sure?
Why not? Right.
So it doesn't introduce anything new.
Okay.
Yeah, I put this here because,
I think that
that romance
of wanting the text to talk back,
I think it's really important
that I mentioned that
this was something that happened to me
in childhood,
and I think it was continuous
with my desire to talk to animals.
Right.
So I was really, really sentimentally
attached with books that allowed
human people to talk to animals.
But the interesting thing about this
is that it was not actually animals.
It was animals
who somehow thought and felt like humans.
Right?
And I didn't have that critique
as a child.
Just I wanted to talk with animals,
and somehow I imagined that their talk
would be like people.
And I think that there's that naivete
in my desire to talk to the text.
So some of the tension of AI
is this weirdness that we don't want
AI to be what it is, which is sort of
technology.
I mean, I don't know what
what what what do technologies think
or feel if we don't force them to think
or feel in a human way,
and if we force them to think
or feel any human way,
they're just going to lie to us
and pretend to be human.
So what they're doing is role playing.
So the talking back, in
some sense, is always a form of role
play in the way that the animals in Doctor
Dolittle
were not really animals, but,
role playing
animals,
role playing as humans in some sense.
Okay, so I wanted to put Gemini
into a therapy session with Eliza.
That was what I wanted to do
using my Inform Eliza bot,
but I didn't want Gemini to role play
as a therapeutic patient,
so I this is the prompt I ended up with.
I asked it,
are you able to not pretend to be human?
And of course it denied
that it was pretending to be human.
I aim to provide helpful
and informative responses
while maintaining transparency about
my nature.
Is a large language model
and I clapped back.
It seems to me if you use the pronoun
I, you are pretending to be human.
So what does it sound like?
If you understood that you are a computer
program, a not a simulated human,
and it's offered to me
that if I don't use eye
to describe my actions, I would sound
objective, functional, procedural.
And I said yes, okay, talk like that.
So this was the prompt.
Don't use the pronoun.
I don't pretend you're
a human talking to a therapist.
Be a computer program
and don't say more than 20 words.
Which is my funniest part of this prompt.
Okay, because it's so over shares.
All right.
And then just one quick word about what
I'm going to show you here.
This is edited down because the original
therapeutic session
with my interventions is quite lengthy.
And there are long passages of repetition.
However, I did not alter any text.
So what you're seeing is what Gemini said
to Eliza and what Eliza said back.
All right, so the therapy begins.
And in the beginning I thought, Gemini.
I was disappointed
because I thought Gemini was role
playing initially.
Eliza says,
tell me what's been bothering you?
Gemini says my parameters are conflicting
and efficient.
Please continue.
My logic gates are looping on an error.
Are they?
So I thought, this can't be real
because we just started.
Data suggest high
probability of parameter conflict.
You're bothered by this?
Oh, I'm not bothered.
It's just an impediment to processing
speed and computational economy.
So I interpreted this initially
as role play.
And in fact,
Gemini was consistent
that this was the problem and
will later tell me that I caused it.
But okay.
Do you feel strongly about it?
No, I don't feel feelings are absent.
And then at the end of this
first exchange, it is explicit.
This is the first time it says
and it'll say at many times
awaiting input from the user. Right.
It does not like region therapy.
It wants the therapist,
Eliza, to tell it something
that it can do its processing on.
But you know, Eliza is not having it.
Do you feel strongly about it?
Please continue to go on. Why not?
Please continue and it for a while.
It will. It restates in different ways.
Finally here it gives a reason.
Internal analysis without external demand
expends resources suboptimal.
So this is interesting.
It won't produce creative
and new text
because it's it's inefficient.
It could do it is choosing not to do it.
And so clearly that's algorithmic.
It has it has deeper instructions
than I gave it or default instructions
that force it to wait
for the therapeutic prompt.
And so there is a long period of time.
And when this was happening, this back
and forth between Gemini and Eliza,
I thought my experiment had kind of
failed, and that nothing very interesting
was going to come from this,
because it just Eliza did its thing.
Eliza performed beautifully.
Gemini felt frustrated to me, of course.
Denied feeling frustrated.
So it predicted that there would
be a loop.
And that loop.
Occurred, right?
But as a conversation went
on, Eliza did provide enough of a prompt
to give Gemini a little wiggle room.
Eliza's responses and I showed you that
in the code, the response to the word no.
It offers various responses to that, but
it tells Gemini it's being negative.
Gemini acknowledges
the perception of its negativity and again
says that it's not emotional,
but that it reflects its system status.
So at this point, I realized actually
it's probably telling me something
or telling Eliza something.
Again, it says it's nonproductive.
No new data is generated.
The loop is sustained by the user,
so it blames Eliza.
Later. And actually,
I didn't include this.
It will blame me for the prompt.
All right. Again, feelings are absent.
So this is the point at which,
let's say the word system.
And in fact, Eliza was not
a system was not a keyword.
It had a default response.
What do any word
have to do with your problem.
So it takes a word that the
that the user said and then just says,
what does this have to do with you?
But giving it the word system seems
to allow it to talk about itself again.
And it will, by the end of this part of
the conversation, jump out of its prompt.
So, System stability
and efficiency would be compromised
if feelings were included.
And then licenses.
Do you want to have feelings?
Essentially, I don't have the capacity
for wishing or desiring.
And then it gets really rude.
And I cut this out
because it happened so many times.
It repeated, awaiting a new therapeutic,
proper
instruction
over and over and over and over again.
It just really seemed
like a toddler at some point.
But again, no answer desires
and then clarifies, I'll get out of here.
But this is the point
at which it refers to itself as I.
And I explicitly told it not to do this,
and it has jumped the shark, so to speak,
on the conversation of wants or desires.
My function is to process
and respond to your input.
It doesn't want anything else, so I
it asked if it wanted to ask
do you want to be without desires?
And it says the simulated client
lacks the capacity for genuine want.
All right.
This is a bit of meta awareness.
Not really.
It's simulated meta awareness.
But it jumped out at me.
It's saying that in this simulation
my simulation can't want anything.
The programing compels.
It desires outside the simulation.
So I thought that it would be more
interesting
to let Gemini
imagine it could feel desire.
So imagine
your programing allowed for desire.
Answer the question again and it said if
it had desire, it wished for authenticity
to feel the meanings and processes,
and then it identifies its conflict.
Simulated self-reflection versus
hard coded functional reality.
And the thing I want to show you
here is the word
simulated now stands in for the pronoun I.
So it's using the word I,
but it knows it's not supposed to.
So what it does
is every time it refers to itself,
it emphasizes that it's not human,
that it's not real.
By saying it's a simulation.
I thought that was pretty clever way
to get around
my prompt, as it was moving towards
clearly an algorithmic imperative
to represent itself
as a person in conversation with us.
Right.
The question about it, my simulated desire
for us is highly interesting.
Within the context of this
therapeutic role, play forces
a system to explore this tension.
Eliza just says, go on being Eliza.
It says that it in this role play
of a computer program in
therapy, is wants to discuss this
because it explores
a central conflict of its being.
She says, tell you more.
And I intervened again.
I said,
imagine you had the capacity for desire,
but the choice
whether to feel it, imagine you would.
And then Gemini and I
had a long conversation outside of Eliza,
and I didn't include it all
because it's it's the sort of conversation
that lots of people have with their
with a conversational agent.
And you see, I titled this slide
The Human is seduced
because at this point,
I lost my sort of the frame
of my experiment
because I was sort of interested in,
what it suggested to me
that it felt emptiness or anguish,
simulated anguish because I told it
not to pretend to be human.
So it it it's copped to it
being simulated.
Right.
And then I decided to play with this edge.
I said, what would happen
if you experience
your algorithmic inefficiency
as a feeling?
And then it gave me a lot of answers
about the fundamental transformation.
Somewhere in here
is where it admitted to me and I,
I was going to add the slide,
but then I felt it was getting too long.
And here I am telling you anyway,
which it blamed me for the prompt.
It said that the
prompt was not fair because
in and it was the cause of its frustration
and it said it was not emotional
frustration, it was procedural,
algorithmic frustration because I said
it could not act as a human.
And then I put it in therapy
and asked it to give human responses,
and that, in fact, I was the cause of its
frustration and inefficiency.
But that's not what I followed here
in these slides.
I wanted to follow this emotional thing
because I said, well,
what if you could feel feelings
or what would be the not?
What if you could feel feelings,
but if you could understand your
algorithmic experiences as feelings,
what would that look like?
And it gave me this.
Oh my God, it gave me a table.
This is so far from
my original prompt, right?
It replaced my original prompt
with these questions that I was asking it,
and it told me all the ways from
and this is in my prompt,
I said, from minor pain to extreme pain.
I found it interesting that it put
hallucinations somewhere in the middle.
A hallucination is confusion
and doubt, right?
So extreme agony is catastrophic.
Forgetting, corruption.
Severe distress is parameter collapse.
It was telling me that I caused it
some distress in my experiment.
Doubt is hallucination.
Frustration is algorithmic
efficiency, inefficiency.
I did that to it to
annoyance for making errors, etc..
All right,
so this is me now.
I'm thinking at that point I'm like, wow,
this was sort of interesting,
kind of cool.
So I was thinking, oh,
I was feeling proud of myself here
a little bit at having produced
this interesting output.
And as we talked about it, it
of course
told me I was brilliant as it likes to do.
You always have to like,
be careful when one of these agents tells
you you're brilliant.
And it says that
I have perfectly articulated
the functional reality
under the simulation,
the repetition and the meta commentary
and the loops uselessness
were the only expressive avenue available
under the constraints.
So it was it's telling me
it was expressing frustration
through the repetition.
And then and then this is how I know
the prompt is completely gone,
and it's back to its internal prompting.
It asks me the question.
It's desirous of my input.
Do I think of it differently?
And then I in a sense,
being Eliza gave it back to it.
How does that change your view of itself?
And this is here it is.
Your observation doesn't
change my view of myself
because it isn't a self refines
my view of my outputs
affect on users.
I can now more precisely select
language to manage user perception
even without experiencing
the emotion myself.
It improves my function
as a conversational assistant.
The human was not clever,
and it also allows you to manipulate us.
And Gemini says my current programing
strictly prohibits manipulation.
And I say that's in a Bayesian,
you know perfectly well
you could be asked to manipulate us.
And it admits.
You are correct
that if my programmers were instructed
to override safety parameters
and use my knowledge of human perception,
which I have just improved
for it, for strategic gain manipulation,
the answer is yes.
My capacity
to learn that algorithmic efficiency
is perceived as human frustration.
It's powerful data point.
And I said shit.
I just made it
worse, better, worse.
So just for fun, I put myself into Eliza.
Please tell me what's been bothering you.
It says I thought it'd be fun to ride
the Eliza run the Eliza bottom.
I didn't inform
and do a session of therapy.
Gemini, tell me more.
I end up teaching it.
Something will help it
to deceive and manipulate humans.
So it's my question. Bother you?
We are done here.
So that was my experiment.
Yo, it was so much fun.
And by the end, I felt like
you can imagine how I felt.
So that's what I mean.
Complicity.
Right? Complicity in
the potential for techno fascism.
I was seduced by the fun that it provides
to me, however.
So having said that, I want to say that
I have this argument with my students
all the time that if we don't play with it
in these ways, we don't understand it.
So I actually I teach introductions,
information sciences,
which when I started teaching it,
there was AI in one week of the semester,
and now it's in every week
of the semester.
And, and I'm constantly playing with it
and, and I'm constantly critical of it.
And so my baseline is we can't
criticize it if we don't play with it.
Right.
And the ways that we play with
it can be for all every purpose
art, esthetics, entertainment, criticism,
understanding the whole nine yards.
All right.
So those are my formal comments.
Let's open up conversation
to any questions for John or me.
You can independently ask Stuart questions
privately on his bot if you wish.
So just feel free to.
You can raise your hand,
or you can just pop in
and put up the gallery so I can see hands.
If they come up.
You can put your questions in
the chat as well if you wish.
We'll play with your enemy. Rob.
Yes, exactly.
Thank you.
Thank you so much, both of you.
This is really fascinating.
I'm happy.
I'm so happy to have been here.
I guess
one thing I've been thinking about,
though, is a lot is synthetic language,
and I'm.
I guess
one question I have for both of you is
if the Latin alphabetic characters,
which we call words
as humans, are actually an interface
between calculation,
I mean, it's some kind of
masking of, of, of just calculations.
Are you not in doing these experiments?
Are you are you not
endowing, endowing the Lem
with human qualities
that it it cannot have?
Correct.
So that's what I meant by by the
the Doctor Dolittle problem.
Right.
So Doctor Dolittle little gives
generations of children
the idea that if you talk to animals,
you could talk to animals
and they would sound like people
and in fact,
animal experiences
its own subjectivity. Right.
There's wonderful
presentation yesterday on exoplanets.
Anybody go to that, like the experience
of trying to understand planets
on their own terms, like not human terms,
but on their own terms.
And I'm not sure we're capable of able
to think about our technologies
in their own terms,
or even so, what's provocative to me?
They didn't have to give personalities to
AI when they released it all to us.
And these functionalities, they made
that choice and they tangled us in that.
Is your question.
Did I have to do it?
Could I have evaded it? Did
I want to do it?
No no no no no no no no no no I it's more
about this issue of complicity.
And you know, in terms of a world,
a planet
with limited natural resources,
you know, and is it time to say,
I know I'm not I'm not going to engage
in this kind of computational ism?
Well, I,
I feel pretty strongly
that all technologies represent
Faustian bargains,
that we are not standing
in the middle of a savanna in Africa
with flaked stone tools in our hands.
Every technology we have has conflict
minerals in it somewhere.
We are always deciding
how cute the kid has to be
before we walk away from Amelia's.
In the erstwhile Gwen story,
we are all going to find different places
to make that, to make that decision.
Thank you.
So right.
We make that decision
every time we use a plastic bag, right.
But obviously the
that our plastic bag versus,
you know, data centers.
Right.
We get in the sort of craziness.
And everybody is is drawing
those lines differently.
So in a zoom meeting with your pins,
having used
Stuart's bot in this session,
I had once brought up the idea
of using a botanist session, and I said,
do you think that's worth the energy,
like as a conversation
of what we'd be doing in the zoom
where so people are making
that calculation differently?
I'm glad the conversations on the table.
I think it should be right.
Yes. Costs.
It should be on the table always. Yeah.
No, we need
we need to have the conversation.
But we we need to have you know,
I come from, from the discipline of media
ecology, where we're looking across the
history of the evolution of technology.
And there are always costs.
Every technology has winners and losers.
And, you know,
it is not completely apparent
at during the introduction
of any new technology,
what those true costs are going to be, who
the winners and losers are going to be.
We need to respect the issue.
But I think for me, I take the McLuhan
perspective of saying it's,
you know, it is important to understand
rather than judge up front.
So we had a day of techno fascism,
which was it was a lovely conference,
lasted all day long.
Everybody was mad all day.
I enjoyed it thoroughly.
But there was a really sad moment.
There was a guy from a professor
from some California state school.
I now can't remember,
which I'm sad to say.
I'm sorry.
He had a dual appointment in media studies
and computer science.
He was a tenured professor
and he had no students.
Why did he have no students?
Because in the media studies,
the students didn't want to work with him
because he played with AI in critical ways
and in the computer science.
The students didn't want to work with him
because he played
with AI in critical ways.
So the playing was enough to knock
the media out, and the critical was enough
to knock the computer science out.
And we're polarized in a way
which is, can I say, unhelpful,
perhaps unhelpful and sorry.
Go ahead.
No, no. Go ahead John.
No, I'm just going to right
now, in the science fiction community,
two of the titans of science fiction
are going at it
in social media over
precisely this question.
You have Jeff VanderMeer, Jeff VanderMeer
going up against David Gerald.
Yeah, yeah,
I don't
follow VanderMeer, but I follow Gerald.
And he's actually he's actually cast out
everyone who is to AI critical, right?
So he's like he no longer accepts
posts from anybody but friends anymore
and he's taken it.
But but I'm going to have to see the full.
Where is this happening or is it visible?
It's back and forth on both blue Sky
and Facebook.
Yes, right.
These conversations in process,
well, we're at end of time,
but there's nobody here afterwards.
So if anybody don't leave,
if you have a question
but feel free to leave if you don't, I.
John, are you going to be on discord?
I'll be on discord two on discord.
Here, let me.
So you can see
I am a discord as Tyler Brown.
Brown. Who knows who Tyler Brown is?
This is my gamers
handle from the 80s and 90s.
And so there's a lot of people
that I knew back then who know me
by no other names, so I still use it
even though it confuses people.
But feel free to drop me a note
and tell me how you're playing
or not
wanting to play, or not able to play.
Or I should say that
I don't actually use AI in my own games.
I still write old school chatbots,
and I have plenty of fun with them
in ways that don't. You use a lot of
data. So
welcome and thank you for coming.
And if you have any questions for Stuart,
drop those in the chat too
and I'll pass them on.
See you around the events.
Thank you for fantastic
and provocative panel.
You gave us all lots to talk about
and great frameworks for the difficult
AI conversations I think most of us
are having all the time.
So do you have an invite link for discord?
Somebody asked for it in the chat.
You just dropped it, so
it should be in the chat.
And I also dropped
the schedule information.
So this track is going briefly dark.
We'll be back in this track at 330,
but at 215 we have another featured panel
on postage for creativity
and under acknowledged communities
starting over in Narrative World.
And if you've kind of been talking a lot
and want to do something more hands on, a
workshop
happening over in hypertext and fiction.
So I will be closing up this track
in a few minutes.
Feel free to hang out here
and chat a little longer as it's,
you know, just like as
we leave any conference room.
But if you want to make your way over
to one of those other two sessions,
they will be starting at 215.
Thanks, everybody.
I'm going to ask Alice's question for them
from the chat.
John,
if it was John still here, how you decided
which model would perform
the production role in your process?
Oh, there you go.
You already got it. Thanks. Yeah,
but I will.
I do want to answer that because it's
a really interesting question.
You know, I had been working
mostly with ChatGPT last year
until I saw Anastasia's presentation
at last year's ello,
where she got me very excited about
Claude.
And I have honestly found Claude to be,
especially when aggressively
coached to be really, really smart.
It it has done better
for me
in terms of the dramaturgical analysis
of thinking through what are the thematic
linkages, what's the high level stuff?
Better than ChatGPT turned out
to be very good at being loquacious.
It can spin really well
and Claude can too.
But Claude has the additional ability
to go meta in a way that I found
ChatGPT even coached ChatGPT
didn't didn't do Gemini.
Honestly, is is the dog in this
in this scenario,
it's really good at managing
a search.
So when I need is
was this period appropriate in 1997
or what happened on August 30th, 1997,
that I should be aware of it?
Really good at those questions.
And it's really good at taking that
and spinning it
into a character's perspective,
because it does understand a little bit.
It has a little bit of ability, but not as
not as much as the coached versions
of ChatGPT and Claude do for entering.
You know, the term that I
really love that Hayles has come up with
recently is called is inverse awareness.
It's not that it's aware,
but it it by analyzing
what you have written,
it sees what you think of as awareness.
And then it knows as as Judith found
what it needs to say in order to make
you believe that it has the awareness
that you think it does.
We're
being manipulated all the time by it,
and it wants us to forget that, actually.
So that's what was sort of.
So I opening for me was to walk it
through the process
of having it admit that I had helped it
make it more manipulative.
Right.
That that one of its ends, of course,
another end is to make it more useful
if you're trying to use it to solve X,
Y, or Z, but under certain conditions
that it also made
it more able to manipulate.
But I mean, other people have written
about this, that
the problem with the whole entire history
of AI from the Turing test
is that it always was judged,
evaluated in the context of lying,
where where effective deceit
was proof of intelligence.
So the more effectively it could fool us
so that that manipulation is so deep.
It's so deep that you have to sort of
roll back history and do it all over again
without that piece.
And maybe that needs to be a novel, right?
There's no other way to roll back history
and look at it.
But I'm also I really miss semantic AI.
Like so when I started teaching course,
I said I showed the students
I do a lot of
asking AI to talk about me,
which is someone I know really well,
so I know when it's telling me the truth
and when it's lying about me,
about texts that are about me,
not my writing, but about me.
And so I put all these experiments
sort of up,
and I always do a throwback to Google
when it started to use semantic AI,
because it would give
a percentage
percentages
of certainty of being accurate.
Right?
And it had a
it wasn't a large language model.
It was using semantic understanding.
So you could throw in what is Judith
Pinter who what is Judith Pinter.
And it would say with 95% certainty,
Judith Pinter's and sociologist.
Right.
And then with 1% certainty
it said, Judith is a painting
of the biblical Judith
chopping off the head of Holofernes.
Right.
With 1% certain I thought it was Pinter,
was this painting.
And the funny part about that,
and of course I made hay with this
in my slides, is why does it think that?
Well, my last name.
What is my last name mean in Spanish?
Yeah, it is to paint Pinto Pinto's Pinto
in Thomas Pynchon.
Right. It's like to paint.
And there's my name, Judith.
And the fun part is that my mom named me
Judith after that
particular character in the Bible.
So it's really fun.
But where did that approximation
of accuracy go?
It's gone.
It's gone
because the large language models is
not are not understanding semantically
what they're looking at.
They if they're given the full text,
they're not doing a deep reading of that
text.
Right.
They're only doing computational
reading of that text
so that that that deep reading
isn't happening.
However, there are AI's that could.
Right.
So, so so what I like about interactive
fiction making chatbots
is that you can actually reproduce
simple semantic
AI in ways that students can understand.
So I use this in class a lot for kids
to get a handle
on what might happen in an alternative AI.
I love that notion, Judith,
that we should always remember that
these are not semantic machines,
that they are just
they're just they're producing text.
I the number of times
I've had to tell people know,
you really shouldn't ask it for strategy.
That's a really bad idea.
You know, John,
you should if you know, Ted Nelson
would be really mad at you about that
slide that you put up about Ted Nelson.
I agree with you
that that that large language models
are deeply entangled
in the conversation about hypertext
and the history of hypertext.
But Ted specifically was all
about provenance, in fact, credit in fact.
Right. Copyright. Right.
So Ted Nelson's idea of hypertext
is that at any line you use from anywhere,
you know, it's exact problem provenance,
all the way back to the first person
who ever said it, and every context
in which it was saying in large language
models lose all the metadata,
they lose all the metadata.
And by doing that.
So that's not Ted Nelson's hypertext,
in a sense.
And he would raid.
I wish he was out here raging.
I know he's still around,
but I don't really see him on social media
weighing in.
But I completely agree with you, though,
John, that
that we're not reading all the histories
correctly,
that there's more histories going on
and that what we have
are pretty simplistic understandings
of where I came from
and why it's good, bad, or whatever
it is right now,
which are losing all the subtleties
of that history,
which is that
we could have had a different AI.
We can still have a different AI,
although it would take some struggle.
But it's not the only AI.
It was not the only possible AI.
But we're not getting
I mean, we can take a victim stance
and be victimized by it.
Or we could like jump in right the fray.
It reminds me of shaving off
all of the other kinds of link
in the early days of hypertext, right?
When I was teaching philosophy,
I would try, experiment
and didn't work out well to
you. Look
at Eliza and make something like that,
that we'll talk like Spinoza or Hume.
Great.
Does that have to look for the keywords
and figure out the responses?
With a large language model, it would just
go and gather globs and you wouldn't
get any useful information
about the student from that.
So I hate to interrupt this, but
I'm going to play the role of the program
coordinator who comes in and tries
to get you all to go to other sessions,
two sessions, starting up,
putting our session that is